<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Narrative of the apprehending, commitment, arraignment, condemnation, and execution of John James, who suffered at Tiburne, Novemb. the 26th, 1661 with several occasional passages and speeches, faithfully collected from such as were eye and ear witnesses : also, an account of the death of several persons since the execution of John James, known to be active and diligent in that matter.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B27136</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">8164198</idno>
  <idno type="VID">204229</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264208417</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing N175</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">08164198</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B27136)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204229)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1235:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Narrative of the apprehending, commitment, arraignment, condemnation, and execution of John James, who suffered at Tiburne, Novemb. the 26th, 1661 with several occasional passages and speeches, faithfully collected from such as were eye and ear witnesses : also, an account of the death of several persons since the execution of John James, known to be active and diligent in that matter.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">James, John, d. 1661.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Fifth Monarchy Men.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:204229:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204229:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204229:2"/>
            <p>A NARRATIVE OF THE APPREHENDING, COMMITMENT, ARRAIGNMENT, CONDEMNATION, And EXECUTION of JOHN JAMES Who Suffered at <hi>TIBURNE, Novemb.</hi> the 26<seg rend="sup">th.</seg> 1661.</p>
            <p>With several occasional <hi>Passages</hi> and <hi>Speeches,</hi> faithfully Collected from such as were Eye and Ear Witnesses.</p>
            <p>Also, An Account of the Death of several Persons since the Execution of <hi>John James,</hi> known to be active and diligent in that matter.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 11.4.</hi>
               </bibl> By it he being Dead yet Speaketh.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the year, 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:204229:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204229:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>FOr Satisfaction of publick Expectation (after much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and pains taken) here is at last presented a <hi>NARRATIVE</hi> of the late <hi>Tryal, Sayings,</hi> and <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings</hi> of <hi>John James,</hi> which as you will find, gives neither gloss nor Descant upon the Matter, nor Commendation of the Person; but simply a plain <hi>Account</hi> of some material <hi>Passages</hi> and <hi>Circumstances</hi> therein, and they Collected with as much exactness as was possible, inserting nothing but what there hath been sufficient Evidence for: But in some things the <hi>Narrative</hi> is much shorter than was desired, or might be expected, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in reference to the <hi>Tryal;</hi> the Relation whereof, for want of a good <hi>Notary</hi> in the Court, and a Copy of the <hi>Record,</hi> comes forth much more imperfect than otherwise it might have done.</p>
            <p>You have here the <hi>Crimes</hi> charged against him, how proved, by whom, and in what manner, with his Defence and avowed Innocency from first to last, and his solemn Appeals to the Lord thereupon, that by some signal Testimony he would manifest the same; of which no judgment is here passed, but submitted to the discerning and impartial Reader, or rather to the Lord, to whom in an especial manner it is committed: So that if there hath been any undue Combination against this poor man, if for some Reason of <hi>State,</hi> rather than for any real Guilt on his part, he was made an Example; if his Judgment and Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, rather than any just Crime, were the cause of his Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, as he so often declared; if submitting to a <hi>Tryal</hi> by
<pb facs="tcp:204229:4"/>the Word of God, he was judged contrary thereto; the Lord in his due time will manifest, and his Blood will most certainly be required; according to that Word, <hi>Jer. 26.14, 15.</hi> which he left with the <hi>Court</hi> at the time of receiving his Sentence: And whether the special hand of the Lord hath already reached some, in a visible execution of Judgment upon them, (since his death) who were so publickly, (and as we fear malitiously) ingaged in that matter, is not here certainly determined, but time may further manifest; only it was thought necessary, to give a <hi>Relation</hi> of the Death of the several Persons, inserted in the end of this Book, which came to hand since this went to Press.</p>
            <p>If thou receive any Spiritual Advantage by his Experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and dying Breathings, give God the Glory, and labour to get an Intrest in Christ, which can only bear up the Soul in a dying hour, and inable to encounter with the greatest dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="narrative_of_the_arrest">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:204229:4"/>
            <head>Some <hi>PASSAGES</hi> at the first taking and apprehending of <hi>John James,</hi> and the Company with him, met together in <hi>Bulstake-Alley</hi> in <hi>White-Chappel,</hi> Octob. <hi>19. 1661.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Congregation being assembled the day above-mentioned, (being the seventh day of the week) in <hi>Bulstake-Alley</hi> (where was the place of their publick Meeting, the Doors being open) continued together the former part of the day in the Worship of God without disturbance; and being again come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the afternoon, continued without interruption till three of the Clock; about which time <hi>John James</hi> was speaking from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. in these words, <hi>For ye are bought with a price, therefore glorifie God in your body, and in your spirit, which are Gods.</hi> About which time one Justice <hi>Chard,</hi> with Mr. <hi>Wood</hi> the Headborough, came to the Meeting-place, Mr. <hi>Wood</hi> commanding him in the King's name to be silent and come down, having spoke Treason against the King: but <hi>John James</hi> taking little notice thereof, and going on upon his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, the Headborough came nearer to him in the middle of the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-place, and commanded him again in the King's name to come down, or else he would pull him down; whereupon the disturbance grew so great he could not proceed, but told the Headborough he would not come down except he was pull'd down; whereupon he pulled him down, and halled him away. The cause of his being apprehended proceeding from one <hi>Tipler</hi> a Pipemaker, Journy-man to a Neighbour near adjoyning, who from their Yard hearing the said <hi>John James</hi> speak a little before, from <hi>Psal.</hi> 8.2. in these words; <hi>Out of the mouthes of Babes and Sucklings hast thou ordained strength be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of thine Enemies, that thou mightest still the Enemy and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venger.</hi> (which words were occasionally spoken to, by way of addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to what another Brother had spoken before) Whereat the said <hi>Tipler</hi> taking offence, went to Justice <hi>Chard</hi> to acquaint him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; but being an Idle fellow, the Justice (as it's said) took not much notice of what he spake, till bringing a Neighbour with him, he was provoked by him to regard his Testimony.</p>
            <p>Whereupon the Justice came forth and went with Mr. <hi>Wood</hi> the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:204229:5"/>Headborough to the Meeting-place, and seized upon him as aforesaid, the said Justice standing at the door: Hereupon an Uproar grew, some crying out in the streets, <hi>Treason, Treason;</hi> the Hamblets were hereupon summoned upon pain of death, many of whom appeared accordingly; and by this time four
<note n="*" place="margin">The said Justices be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that day sat near that place at the Half-Moon Tavern, about the Lieutenancy.</note> Justices of the Peace were come together, to wit, the Lieutenant of the Tower, Justice <hi>Bide,</hi> Justice <hi>Swallow,</hi> and Justice <hi>Chard; John James</hi> in the mean time was committed to the custody of the Headborough, who carried him to a Tavern near thereunto, where several Souldiers and other loose people came about him, scoffing and blaspheming, some taking Wine and saying, <hi>I drink to you in the spirit;</hi> and others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rude, and reproved by the Officer, said, <hi>I would only speak to him a few words in the spirit:</hi> in this time the rest of the Meeting by se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens were brought before the Justices (being at an house near the Meeting-place) who tendring the Oath of Allegiance unto them, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted those that refused, some to <hi>Newgate,</hi> both men and women, being guarded thither by the Hamblets; afterwards the same Justices entring the Meeting-place sate down about the Table with their Clerk and (one Major <hi>Manly</hi> standing by) did send for <hi>John James,</hi> and in the mean time the Licut. of the Tower read a Paper which he pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out of his pocket, saying, he would reade to them what doctrine was preached there that day, being of the nature of a Charge, which they drew up from <hi>Tiplers</hi> mouth against <hi>John James,</hi> demanding of certain women (relating to the Meeting, yet detained, and whose names they were then taking) how they could hear such things as those? To which they unanimously replyed in the fear of the Lord, That they never heard such words, as they should answer it before the Lord, and they durst not lye: who replyed, They had but their <hi>words,</hi> but they had others <hi>Oathes</hi> for it: who made answer in the Prophets words, <hi>Psal.</hi> 102.8. <hi>They which were made against them, had sworn against them.</hi> By this time <hi>John James</hi> was brought into the Meeting-place, and the Lieutenant (looking upon him) said to the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, What have you no better a holder-forth than he? <hi>John James</hi> said, that the way of the Lord was and is many times, to use the poorest of his People to do his Work, alledging also the Apostles words, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.27. that <hi>he chooseth the weak and foolish things of the world to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:204229:5"/>the mighty:</hi> Then said the Lieut. of the Tower, What you are a Jew. <hi>John James</hi> said, that in one sense he was a Jew, and in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other sense not, repeating those words of the Apostle in <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. last. <hi>For he is not a Jew that is one outwardly, neither is that Circumcision which is outward in the flesh; but he is a Jew which is one inwardly, and Circumcision is that of the heart in the spirit, whose praise is not of men, but of God.</hi> The Lieut. asked him, whether he had not been before him before this? who answered, he had: and whether he had not been civilly used? he replyed, Yea, and for his civility he thanked him: Then the Lieutenant asked him, if he wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot counselled for to take heed for the future? he answered. Yea, and he had taken it so far as he could with a good Conscience: upon which the Lieut. told him he should stretch for it, <hi>and if he were not hang'd he would be hang'd for him. John Iames</hi> told him, he was not carefull in that matter, and that they could do no more than they should be suffered by the Lord to do: The Lieut. told him, he thought he was not care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, for he had a mind to be hang'd as some of his holy Brethren that went before him. <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> desired he would not speak so lightly. The Lieut. spake something also about the <hi>Fifth Kingdom,</hi> and asked him, whether it was not his Principle? who told him he did own the <hi>Fifth Kingdom</hi> Which must come: whereupon they laughed one upon another and said, <hi>Now they had it from his own mouth.</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing also was charged upon him about his learning to sound a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, in order to a Rising with <hi>Venners Party;</hi> To which he said, there was a Friend of his who lay in his house, minding to go to Sea, being to learn to sound, desired he might have liberty to be taught in his house, but he never learned himself, neither was he one of those in that Rising, judging it to be a rash act. Then the Lieut. of the Tower called in Capt. <hi>Hodgskin,</hi> who commanded the Party of Soldiers that stood at the door, and said, Take this man, be carefull of him, and commit him Close Prisoner to <hi>Newgate.</hi> So they carried him away with his <hi>Mittimus</hi> hereafter expressed.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Keeper of the Goale of <hi>Newgate,</hi> or his Deputy.</head>
                  <p>Middles. <hi>THese are in the Kings Majesties Name to require you to receive into your Custody the body of</hi> John James, <hi>whom we send you herewith, being taken this present day at a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:204229:6"/>Conventicle, or private Meeting, in the Parish of</hi> White-Chappel, <hi>and there speaking in the audience of the People present, treasonable words against his Majesties Royal Person; you shall therefore keep him Close Prisoner until further order, and this shall be your Warrant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given under our hands</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>this</hi> 19th <hi>day of</hi> October, 1661.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>John Robinson, <hi>Lieut. of the Tower.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Thomas Bide.</item>
                           <item>Edward Chard,</item>
                           <item>Thomas Swallow.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>After that <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> was sent away according to the <hi>Mittimus</hi> afore-mentioned, the Witnesses were called in and further examined, and forthwith a Paper was presented to one of them (being as was sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed the substance of what <hi>Tipler</hi> had before sworn to) which being read with a low voice, the Relator could not hear, but this he saw, that one of the Witnesses refused to take his Oath, saying, That there were many words in the Paper which he did not hear: but the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices said, That this which was written, and that which was heard, was all to one purpose, therefore take it; but he refused it again: yet it being tendred once more, with much perswasions, entreaties, and threatnings to send him to Prison if he refused it, he took it; after which the Lieutenant said, he knew nothing to the contrary but that this business might be worth to them 100 l. a piece: after this <hi>Os<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn</hi> (who was a Seaman) said, I cannot stay, but must go to Sea for a livelihood, for I am poor: Then Justice <hi>Chard</hi> said to the Lieut. of the Tower, Let him be entred in the Tovver, or upon some Ship, to receive the Kings Pay till the business be over; bidding him come to the Tovver accordingly the next morning. As they vvere going avvay, a vvoman and friend of the Seamans being present and heard vvhat passed, said, that his Oath vvas not to be taken: Then the Lieut. asked vvhat she vvas, saying that she vvould fain seduce the Witnesses, and that she deserved to be sent to <hi>Newgate:</hi> to vvhich she replyed saying. You may do vvhat you please, but I speak the truth, and knovv that his vvord is not to be taken: after this they said to the Seaman as they vvere going avvay, be not seduced by her; and further said, that if he did not stand to his Oath, he should be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, vvith other threatning vvords, and so they departed. And it is further asserted by several persons that vvere upon the place vvhen <hi>Osburn</hi> vvas svvorn, vvho immediatly demanded of him vvhat it vvas
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:204229:6"/>he had swore unto, desiring him to tell them the vvords, vvho seemed at that time to be very sad, telling them that he could not remember the vvords except he heard them named over again; upon which also some of the Guard themselves hearing him speak thus, said to him, that they would not be in his condition for all the vvorld. Sometime after this, several spake unto the said <hi>Bernard Osburn,</hi> questioning him about the Oath he had taken; he declared that he had sworn to he knew not vvhat, being forced thereto through fear and hopes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lease; That the said <hi>Bernard Osburn</hi> intending not to stand to his Oath, went to his Ship towards the <hi>Hope</hi> in order to the Sea-voyage he was engaged in, but not long after came a Warrant from the Lieut. of the Tower, to require his appearance in the Court as one of the Witnesses, which was directed to his Brothers house in <hi>Wapping</hi> where he used to lodge, but his Sister acquainted them that he was gone to Sea sometime before: and they demanding where? she said, I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose he may be in the <hi>Downs</hi> by this time; at which the Messenger was much offended, threatning him greatly, which occasioned her speedy coming to the Lieut. of the Tower, vvho in great vvrath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, how long he had been gone, and what Ship he was upon? vvhich she signified unto him, and accordingly he forthwith sent his Marshal to demand him from his Ship, vvhich was performed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly; and vvhen he vvas come, they threatned to have him hang'd, if he did not stand to his Evidence, but if he did he should have all his Charges born, and a Reward for his pains: and from this time he was kept in the Marshal's hands at the Kings charge, till the Tryal was over: After this the said <hi>Osburn,</hi> with the other Witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, were divers times under private Examination by the Kings Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel and Atturney and Solicitor General, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Evidence being prepared, and all things in readiness for a Tryal, <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> having been in <hi>Newgate</hi> from the 19th of the 8th month, was appointed the 14th of the 9th month to appear at the Kings-Bench Bar in order to his Tryal.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="trial_proceedings">
            <head>His ARRAIGNMENT and TRYAL.</head>
            <div n="1" type="day">
               <head type="sub">What passed the first day, <hi>Novemb. 14.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEing carried in a Coach to <hi>Westminster</hi> by the Under-Sheriff and brought to the Kings-Bench Bar, Chief Justice <hi>Forster,</hi> Justice
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:204229:7"/>
                  <hi>Mallet,</hi> Justice <hi>Twisden</hi> and Justice <hi>Windam,</hi> being Judges upon the Bench: he was commanded, according to custom, to hold up his hand, and he did so, and told them he did hold up his hand to signifie he was there to answer to what should be laid to his charge: but he held up his hand with his glove on, which some were offended at, and told him he must pull it off: <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> answered, it was all one to him to hold up his hand with it off or on; and then he did pull off his glove and held up his hand, and then his Charge was read.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="indictment">
                           <head>The Substance of the INDICTMENT.</head>
                           <p>HE stood indited by the name of <hi>John James,</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="1">1. <hi>For compassing and imagining the Death of the King.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="2">2. <hi>For endeavouring to levy War against the King.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="3">3. <hi>For endeavouring a change of the Government. And in this his compassing, imagining, and contriving the Kings Death, he had maliciously, traiterously, and by instigation of the Devil, not having the fear of God before his eyes, declared these words.</hi> (1.) <hi>That the King was a bloody Tyrant, a Blood-sucker and Blood-thirsty man, and his Nobles the same.</hi> (2.) <hi>That the King and his Nobles had shed the Blood of the Saints at</hi> Charing-Cross, <hi>and the Blood of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters in</hi> Scotland. (3.) <hi>That the King was brought in to this end, to fill up the measure of his Iniquity; and that the Kings Cup of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity had filled more within this last year than in many years before.</hi> (4.) <hi>That he did bemoan that they had not improved their Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity when they had power in their hands, and that he did say it would not be long before they had Power again, and then they would improve it better; and that he did bewail the Apostacy of the People of God, and say, they had not fought the Lords Battels thorowly, but when the Lord should give Power to them again, and give his Work into their hands, they would do it better.</hi> (5.) <hi>That the Death and Destruction of the King drew very near.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>The Inditement being read, the Clerk called upon <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> to answer to his Charge, and plead <hi>guilty,</hi> or <hi>not guilty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> desired before they did proceed, that he might have a Copy of his Charge, and time to consider of it.</p>
               <p>The Lord Chief Justice answered him, that a Copy of his Charge was not allowed in cases of High Treason, and he told him he must
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:204229:7"/>plead guilty, or not guilty, or else a worse thing would follow.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John James</hi> answered, he humbly conceived it was his priviledge as an <hi>English-man,</hi> and till he had that he was not free to plead one way or other. He alledged that Chief Justice <hi>Cook</hi> had declared it good Law, And that Judge <hi>Heath</hi> had declared it also good Law, and that he did at <hi>Oxford</hi> give <hi>John Lilburn</hi> a Copy of his Charge, being arraigned there for High Treason.</p>
               <p>Then one of the Kings Counsel told him, that the Law would not grant him a Copy of his Charge in case of Felony, much lesse in case of High Treason; and told him, if he would not plead, they would proceed against him as a person contemning the Court, and look upon him as a Mute.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John James</hi> made answer, seeing he was over-ruled, he pleaded <hi>Not guilty</hi> neither in <hi>form</hi> nor <hi>matter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Clerk asked him how he would be tryed?</p>
               <p>He answered, <hi>By the Law of God;</hi> at which the Lawyers gave a great hisse, And</p>
               <p>It was answered thus, or to this effed, It was not a place or time to talk of the Laws of God. But <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> was vvilling to urge it again, That seeing the Judge did sit there as Judge of the Law, and of Gods Law as they thought, it was meet they should give him liberty to appeal to Gods Law.</p>
               <p>Whereupon the Judge told him he must proceed according to their Law, or else a worse thing would follow, and say, <hi>By God and the Country.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> answered, he was ignorant in their Law, and knew not what snare there might be in it, never having been at any Bar be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and therefore desired him he would open the terms, what they meant by <hi>God,</hi> and what they meant by the <hi>Country.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Judge answered, God forbid but he should open the tearms: By <hi>God</hi> (said he) is meant your first demand, to wit, the Law of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> askt him, why then his first demand was not granted?</p>
               <p>The Judge said, God forbid but that you should so be tryed, but you must use the form of the Court.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> said, If it were so he was satisfied.</p>
               <p>And by the <hi>Country</hi> (saith the Judge) Twelve <hi>Middlesex</hi> men, men of truth, that would judge impartially between the King and him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> said, if that be the meaning, he put himself upon the tryal of <hi>God and the Country.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:204229:8"/>
               <p>When this was done, <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> was sent by a <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> to the Kings-Bench Prison in <hi>Southwark,</hi> and there continued till the 29<seg rend="sup">th</seg> day of <hi>November,</hi> and then was brought again to the Kings-Bench Bar at <hi>Westminster</hi> to his further tryal.</p>
               <p>In this interval betwixt the Commitment and Tryal, upon the first day of the week, being the 18th of <hi>Novemb. Iohn Iames</hi> received a Letter from a Person of Note, to advertise him that there were such a Jury of life and death impanelled to proceed upon him as had not been for many years before, being all pickt men, and most of them Knights and Gentlemen, and that if he did not except against them, or most of the chief of them, he was a dead man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="day">
               <head>The second dayes Tryal.</head>
               <p>Upon the 19. <hi>Novemb.</hi> he appeared the second time at the Kings-Bench Bar, according to the Order of the Court, where were present,
<list>
                     <item>The Judges
<list>
                           <item>Sir <hi>Rob. Foster,</hi> Chief. Justice.</item>
                           <item>Sir <hi>Mallet,</hi> Justice.</item>
                           <item>Sir <hi>Thomas Twisden,</hi> Justice.</item>
                           <item>Sir <hi>Waddam Windam,</hi> Justice.</item>
                           <item>Sir <hi>Jeoffry Palmer,</hi> Atturney General.</item>
                           <item>Sir <hi>Heneage Finch,</hi> Solicitor General.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Kings Counsel
<list>
                           <item>Serj. <hi>Maynard,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Serj. <hi>Glynne.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Serj. <hi>Wilde.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Serj. <hi>Keeling.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Witnesses names appearing in the Court.
<list>
                           <item>Alderman <hi>Chard.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iohn Tipler.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Bernard Osburn.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The fourth Witness his name not yet known.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>The names of the Jury.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Charles Pitfield,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ralph Halsaye,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thomas Eglefield,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Daniel Charlwood,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ambrose Hanburough,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Anthony Hall,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Humphry Higgens,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thomas Snow,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Cole,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thomas Ʋpnel,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Gilbert Mese,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Blunt.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The Witnesses and Jury being called into the Court, <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> having excepted against divers Knights and Gentlemen prickt for his Jury, and the fore-named standing for his Jury; The Clerk did <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> hold up his hand as before: he did so, and again told them it was to signifie that he was there (and then they laughed) and the Judge said, O ho, are you come?</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:204229:8"/>
               <p>Afterwards the Inditement being read again, the Clerk proceeded to tell the Court for what he was endited and arraigned, and that he pleaded <hi>not guilty,</hi> and had put himself upon <hi>God and the Country</hi> for tryal, and therefore told the Jury they were to judge between the King and him in that matter.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <head>Serjeant <hi>Keeling</hi> his Speech.</head>
                           <p>Hereupon Serjeant <hi>Keeling,</hi> one of the Kings Counsel, stept up and said, My Lord, and you Gentlemen of the Jury, <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> prisoner at the Bar stands indited for High Treason, for that he, with other disaffected persons, enemies unto the Government of the King, being assembled at <hi>Bulstake-Alley</hi> in <hi>White-Chappel,</hi> not having God before his eyes, but being moved by the instigation of the Devil, spake and published these words, <hi>viz. That King</hi> Charles <hi>was a blood-thirsty tyrannical King, and that the Nobles of</hi> England <hi>were blood-thirsty and tyrannical men, and that the Cup of their Iniquity was begun to be filled by the shedding of the blood of the Covenanters in</hi> Scotland, <hi>and that it was almost filled by the shedding of the blood of the Saints this time twelve-month, and that the time of their destruction was near at hand; and did condole the neglect of the Opportunity and price they had put into their hands, and that if ever the like Occasion were administred unto them again they would fight the Lords Battels more effectually than they had done before:</hi> And (said he) if we prove that these words were spoken by <hi>Iohn Iames,</hi> you are to find him guilty of High Treason; (and so he sate down.)</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Then stood up Sir <hi>Ieoffry Palmer,</hi> Atturney General.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <head>The substance of Sir <hi>Jeoffry Palmer's</hi> Speech.</head>
                           <p>First, he spake of the Antiquity of Monarchy, and did fully assert the present Government: then, by way of reflexion, he reviewed the 20. years troubles that had passed over our heads in these Nations, and that the Vessel of this Commonwealth had been beaten and blown upon the waves and billows of a tempestuous raging Sea, being almost broken to pieces and like utterly to be lost, unless God by a miraculous providence had restored his Majesty <hi>Charles the second</hi> to his Crown and Dignity, for which (he said) <hi>ever blessed be his Name.</hi> Then he observed that the beginning of our sorrows was by the seditious preaching of some discontented Ministers in this Nation, and about this City. Then he told them how much care the Law had taken for the preservation of his Majesties Person and Government, and that it
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:204229:9"/>was as much Treason in the <hi>heart</hi> as in the <hi>act, Mens rea facit reum.</hi> Then he did descant upon the words of the Indictment and opened them, and told the Jury, that, according to the Law of <hi>England,</hi> they were Treason, for which he ought to dye; and then sate down.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Then the Court called <hi>Iohn Tipler</hi> the first Witness, the Judge bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him look upon the Prisoner. Serj. <hi>Glynne</hi> asked him what he could say concerning the words spoken by <hi>Iohn Iames?</hi> Who said (at the time in the Indictment alledged, which was on Saturday) he was at a house near adjoyning unto the place where they usually did meet, and that about two of the Clock in the afternoon he stood at a Window in a Yard, next adjoyning to the Meeting-place, and saw <hi>Iohn Iames,</hi> the person at the Bar, preaching (as they call it, said he) and repeated the words that were opened by Serj. <hi>Keeling</hi> exactly, only further, that he did wonderfully adore <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> saying, <hi>That every finger of his was a Champion, and that when they had Power again they should do the work most thorowly;</hi> and said, that thereupon he told it presently to a Justice, and afterwards to a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of his, who was in an extream fright and horror, and so they both went together to Alderman <hi>Chard</hi> Justice, who then came immediatly and surprized and seized upon them, the vvomen only they let go, but the men the Justice did commit to Prison that would not take the Oath of Allegiance; That they seized <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> in the Pulpit where he was preaching when they came in. The Court askt him what time of the day it was? and he said it was about two of the clock in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon. And they asked him where he stood? and he said, he stood directly oppsit in a Window in a Yard next adjoyning unto the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-place, and that he could easily discern him. Demanding of him some other Questions that might induce the Jury to believe the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence given was neither with thought of Malice to the Prisoner, nor of hope of Reward
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>But the said</hi> Tipler <hi>(as upon good ground is reported) is since taken into service under the Lieut. of the Tower.</hi>
                  </note>, then the Court gave the Prisoner leave to ask <hi>Tipler</hi> what Questions he pleased.</p>
               <p>The Exception that <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> took unto the Witness, was, That it was a hard thing for him to swear that he was the person that was then preaching, he being without the Window, which might intercept his sight. To that he answered, that he knew him very well, and that he was not deceived.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:204229:9"/>
               <p>Another Witness was Alderman <hi>Chard</hi> the Justice, who said he could say nothing as to the words that were spoken, but that so soon as <hi>John Tipler</hi> came to him and informed of the words spoken by <hi>John James,</hi> he enquired the place where it was, and immediatly he and his Clerk and the Constable hasted thither, where they found <hi>Iohn James</hi> preaching, and about thirty or forty assembled there to hear him; and said, he there seized <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> and pulled him out of the Pulpit where he was preaching; and all those men that would not take the Oath of Allegiance he committed, but the women he let go. So the Court asked him, if it were at the same time alledged in the Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? and he said, Yea.</p>
               <p>Another Witness was a Yorkshire man, whose name we know not; who coming into the Court, was commanded to look upon the Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner at the Bar, and declare what he heard him say: Who answered, he was at <hi>Tiplers</hi> house, and heard very loud speaking, which caused him to come out and hearken, and he heard very dangerous words. The Judge asked him what those dangerous words were? he said he could remember no more than this, that one said, <hi>That the Lord had a great Work to do for his People,</hi> and <hi>that they were the People that must do it.</hi> The Judge askt him, if he heard nothing concerning the Kings Cup of Iniquity? to which he answered, No. And they bid him look upon the Prisoner at the Bar, and askt if that were the man? he answered, he could not say that he was the man.</p>
               <p>Whereupon <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> desired the Judge to ask him, <hi>if he was the man?</hi> and he turned his face towards <hi>Iohn Iames,</hi> as if he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected his speech to him, and said, <hi>he could not say he was the man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another was <hi>Bernard Osburn,</hi> whom the Judge commanded to look upon the Prisoner at the Bar, and tell the Court what he heard him say concerning the King and the Power that were now in being.</p>
               <p>Hereupon <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> told <hi>Osburn,</hi> he hoped he was a man of some Conscience and Integrity, and that he feared wrongfully to take away the Life of a man, and how great a sin it was, especially to shed the Blood of them that feared the Lord.</p>
               <p>Then the Court askt the Witness, where he was when the words were spoken? he said he was in the Meeting-place, and he said he heard <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> say, <hi>That King</hi> Charles <hi>was a blood-thirsty tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical King, and that the Nobles of</hi> England <hi>were blood-thirsty; that he had drunk pritty deep of the Blood of the Saints already, in that he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:204229:10"/>had shed their blood twelve moneths agone at</hi> Charing-Cross, <hi>and the blood of the Covenanters in</hi> Scotland, <hi>and that God had brought him in to that end, to fill up the measure of his Iniquity, and he had filled it up more in twelve moneths than in many years before.</hi> They askt him if heard nothing concerning the Lords Battels? and he told them (as though he had forgot it) that he heard him say, <hi>That they should have Power in their hands, and that then they should fight the Lords Battels more thorowly.</hi> And they askt him if he heard any thing concerning the Ruin of the King? he answered, Yes, he heard him say, <hi>That the Ruine of the King was very near.</hi> Then they askt him, if those were the words? he said, he could not say they were the same words, but to the same substance.</p>
               <p>Having done this, the Judge told <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> he had liberty to speak for himself.</p>
               <p>Whereupon he desired the favour of the Court to those Witnesses he had attending the Court in respect of <hi>Bernard Osburn,</hi> Whereupon four Witnesses were called into the Court, that gave Evidence that this <hi>Bern Osburn</hi> confessed to them, he had sworn against <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> he knew not vvhat: one of them declared further and more largely (that was near marriage to <hi>Bernard Osburn</hi>) that he had told her, <hi>he did not only swear he knew not what, but that he was affrighted into what he swore:</hi> he did say, That what he swore to, was first sworn to by another man, and then brought to him in writing. The former Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses declared, That moreover they desired to know of <hi>Bernard,</hi> what he had sworn against <hi>Iohn Iames,</hi> and he told them, <hi>he could not tell except he heard the words repeated;</hi> (though <hi>B. Osburn</hi> denyed in the face of the Court that ever he said any such things.) <hi>John James</hi> then told the Court, he had several Witnesses attending the Court that were free, if they pleased, to prove, that the words charged upon him were not spoken. The Judge told him he might call in as many Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses as he would, vvhereupon <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> called in four Witnesses more, all which did testifie in the face of the Court, <hi>that the words charged upon him were not spoken;</hi> and the Court did, as before, give them the hearing.</p>
               <p>Then the Judge bid the Jury take notice what had been spoke by the Kings Witnesses and his. And then the Court told <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> that now he had free leave to speak for himself, as much and as long as he pleased, if he had called all his Witnesses; and told him that when the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:204229:10"/>Kings Counsel had concluded he could speak no more, but now he might say as much as he pleased. Then he spake with much liberty and freedom, the Court and all present giving attention to what he said, which was to this purpose.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <head>John James <hi>his Defensive Speech.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>HE said he had somewhat to say, first, as to the form of the Charge, <hi>viz. That he had maliciously, wickedly, traiterously, and by the instigation of the Devil, not having the fear of God before his eyes, &amp;c.</hi> He told them that in the fear of God he did deny it, and told them he had not a malicious thought against the Person of the King, but desired the salvation of his soul, as of his own; that he had not dealt malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously against the King, neither was instigated thereto by the Devil, and that by the goodness of the Lord, what he had done, he had done it in the fear of God; neither could he be judged, as he told them, as a malicious person against the King, in regard he never had any publick Imployment in the Nation, either against this King in being, or his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, being a man of no account in the world, having not worn a sword this 11 years; and therefore desired they would in their understanding clear him from this Charge, as a person malicious against the King; And further he said, he was a person that could not be supposed to have in his eye any thing of advantage in the world in so acting against the King. And as to the matter of the Charge; whereas it runs <hi>that I</hi> John James <hi>had compassed, imagined and contrived the Death of the King; Iohn Iames</hi> told the Court he did not well understand what they meant by <hi>compassing the death of the King,</hi> as compassing and imagining is ordinarily taken; he had not, neither was he capable of endeavouring the <hi>Kings Death,</hi> nor the <hi>Change of the Government,</hi> being a mean inconsiderable person, a man that had lived upon his Calling. And as to those particulars lastly charged upon him, he said, he was not guilty of them, he did not say <hi>the King was a bloody Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, a blood-sucker, a blood-thirsty man,</hi> that in the fear of the Lord he did utterly deny, neither did he say any thing tending thereto. He further said, he did not say <hi>the King had shed the blood of the Saints at</hi> Charing-Cross <hi>this time twelve moneth:</hi> He did not say, <hi>they, when they had Power in their hands, would improve it more thorowly for God, and that we did not sight the Lords Battels thorowly.</hi> And whereas he was charged for contending for <hi>Cromwel,</hi> and that Power (that God had so eminently wiped off from the stage) he said he did declare
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:204229:11"/>against that Power, and were averse to it, and did suffer under it in his measure; and told them he did not stand there as <hi>Cromwels Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate.</hi> Then did he endeavour to speak more particularly to the Jury, letting them know that in a secondary way his life was in their hands; and it was, in the eye of reason, in their power to save or destroy him; and wished them to have a care of shedding Innocent Blood, and told them <hi>because of Innocent Blood the Land did mourn,</hi> to wit, for the Blood shed in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes and King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth; and if there were any Innocent Blood shed since, he desired no more may be added to it: He told them he did desire they would act conscienci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously and not be over-awed by any man; he told them they were his Judges in Law of matter of fact, and desired them to be tender of his Blood. He said, he should say very little more for himself, but one word for the Lord, and therfore desired he might have his fear before him; and although he was the poorest and meanest for such a work, yet he was called forth, and did declare, <hi>That the Lord Jesus Christ was King of Nations, as well as King of Saints, and that the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all Kingdoms did of right belong to him,</hi> and he quoted <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. <hi>And the seventh Angel sounded, and there were great voices in Heaven, saying, The Kingdoms of this world are become the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of our Lord and of his Christ, and he shall reign for ever &amp; ever.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>And when he had so spoke, the Lord Chief Justice <hi>Foster</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted him, saying, <hi>Hold sirrah, sirrah, you think you are in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle in</hi> White-Chappel <hi>preaching,</hi> and thereupon commanded the Clerk to reade the Act of Parliam. entituled, <hi>An Act for the preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Kings Person and Government,</hi> wherein was exprest to this purpose, <hi>That whosoever shall contrive or endeavour to levy War against the King or Government, &amp;c. or endeavour to compass or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive the Death of the King, his Wound or Maim; or that by Printing, Preaching, Writing, or other speaking, endeavour the same; then every such person and persons shall be lookt upon as Traytors to the King, and shall be proceeded against as in the case of High Treason, &amp;c.</hi> Which when the Clerk had read,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John James</hi> desired liberty to speak, desiring the Court to produce a Statute that would reach his Case, for that did not, but the Case of such as had endeavoured to levy War against the King, or had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>past or contrived his Death or Maim; but he had not contrived or compast the Death of the <hi>King,</hi> or the Change of the Government
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:204229:11"/>within or without his Dominions, therefore desired a Statute might be produced that might reach his Case, for he conceived that was short</p>
               <p>The Judge told him; it fully reached his Case.</p>
               <p>And one of the Kings Council made Answer, That it reached him in every Case.</p>
               <p>And another of the Council said, Treason was the first conception, and the first evil thought in the heart, and Treason was made visible by <hi>Preaching,</hi> or <hi>Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> or <hi>Speaking, &amp;c.</hi> which was a manifestation of the Things that were in the heart.</p>
               <p>This being spoken, the Judge asked him, if he had any more to say for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and told him, if he did not speak now, the Kings Council would enter upon their Plea, and then he must speak no more for himself.</p>
               <p>He told them, he had one word to the Iury, which he desired to lay before them, it was a scripture written in the 29 of <hi>Isaiah</hi> 21. <hi>That make a man an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender for a word, and lay a snare for him that reproveth in the Gate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereupon the Judge told him, it was not to be born, for he did enveigh against the Parliament. Though,</p>
               <p>He said, he had not the least thought of the Parliament, but he spake it to let the Jury know, that if he were guilty of those words, there was no Law of God to take away a mans Life for words.</p>
               <p>Hereupon the Kings Council pleaded severally one after another.</p>
               <p>First Serjeant <hi>Glyn</hi> stood up and said, Brother <hi>Maynard,</hi> Shall we not Answer something to what the Prisoner hath objected? So <hi>Glynne</hi> began.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <head>The Substance of Serjeant <hi>Glynn's</hi> Speech.</head>
                           <p>He told the Jury, That if they proved the words alledged in the Indictment sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantially, though it were not Adequate thereunto in every <hi>Tittle</hi> and <hi>Iota,</hi> yet it was sufficient to satisfie their consciences, and to find the Prisoner guilty of High Treason.</p>
                           <p>First he began with the Exception taken unto the first Witnesse, that he stood without the window, and therefore could not easily discern the visage and physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ognomy of the Prisoner that was there a preaching. He told them, He had sworn expresly it was the same person, and that, as he came in into the Yard, he was there a preaching, and as he went away to the Justice of peace he saw him, and the Justice did seize the same person and find him preaching when he came; and therefore it must be him and no other. And told them, that the Witnesse could have no end in discovering of it, for if he had kept silence he had consented, and so been guilty of misprision of Treason.</p>
                           <p>Then said he, as to the Exception taken against the fourth Witnesse, that he said he swore he knew not what, and could not tell what he had sworn to.</p>
                           <p>He said, This was no cause to Reject this Evidence; For, peradventure he could not well call to mind, the several words that were spoken, or peradventure he would not tell them, because he might suppose that they were sent to ensnare him in his evidence, that they might make it void.</p>
                           <p>Then as to the Witnesses that were brought on the part of the Prisoner, to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stify, that no such words were spoken; he said, as to that he must refer it unto the consciences of the Iury. But he said, he conceived that it was altogether imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:204229:12"/>For the Question is not, what he did not say, but what he did say. They say that he did not say these words, but they do not say what he did.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Then stept up Sergeant <hi>Maynard</hi> and said.</p>
               <p>That as to the Evidence of those three persons, he said, his Brother <hi>Glynne</hi> had spoken so much, and so well, that he could add no more, or very little; and urged the same things that Serjeant <hi>Glynne</hi> did; and further said that the Prisoner spoke much of his integrity, and innocency; I believe (saith he) Gentlemen of the Jury, never was there any offender, or the vilest miscreant in the world that would ever have received the reward of his doings if his own excuse and protesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion might have saved him.</p>
               <p>Then he said, As for the blood of the Saints that was spilt this time twelve-month, he said they were sad Saints, such Saints (said he) as would have cut all our throates.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>John James</hi> desired to be heard one word, that that Gentleman had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truly alledged against him, but the Court refused to allow him the liberty.</p>
               <p>Then stood up Sir <hi>Heneage Finch,</hi> Solicitor general.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <head>The Substance of Sir <hi>Heneage Finch</hi> his Speech.</head>
                           <p>My Lord, and you Gentlemen of the Jury, be it known unto you, and to all that hear me this day, That the Prisoner at the Bar is not attained for his Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence or Religion, but for <hi>Treason</hi> and <hi>Rebellion,</hi> for horrid <hi>Treason</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion,</hi> for spurning against the meekest King in the Earth. His Majesty, to the great and unexpressable grief of his heart, did not think there was a person so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, left within his Dominions, that would have lifted up the heel against him, after 20 Years rejecting of his Majesty and his Royal Father, and having also conferred this grace upon us, to reduce us to a state of innocency, he could not think there was any Gaul left in our hearts, or any guile to be found in our months.</p>
                           <p>He then prest his <hi>Treason</hi> upon the Consciences of the Jury, who as he told them, would affright their Consciences with his Innocency. And told them, how that the punishment of this Offendor might affright the like Malefactors for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And said that there were a People, that under the pretence of Religion had the Liberty of Conscience allowed by the King for a time, till they were better informed, but <hi>this man, and those of his mind, are none of those men;</hi> but they endeavour not onely to destroy the <hi>Monarch,</hi> but <hi>Monarchy it self;</hi> not only in <hi>England,</hi> but all the world over, this is the principle that they are of, therefore I desire the Jury to take notice, what may be their duty upon that account. And that when the Prisoner was preaching that pernitious Sermon, he prest it with the peril of their salvation, and now would affright you upon the account of innocent blood; but you shall find, if his blood be rightly and swiftly pursued, it may be a means of preventing the shedding of the blood of thousands, for the time to come. And withal did desire them to consider further, that the great trouble this Nation had undergone for these 20 Years last past, sprung from Pulpits, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles, and seditious Preaching, and therefore if these Causes were taken away, it might prevent such evil Effects for the future. And said, That as to the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence he had produced, it had been well spoke to by the two Serjeants that spoke last: And as to that Evidence by the women, he said, they had no reason to tell
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:204229:12"/>what was said by <hi>John James,</hi> for thereby they would make themselves guilty of misprision of Treason, which is to be punished with perpetual imprisonment, confiscation of Goods, and the loss of the profits of Lands during life.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>That's well observed, said my Lord to the Solicitor.</p>
               <p>Then Judge <hi>Foster</hi> endeavoured further to inform the Jury, and to incense them against his principle, telling them, that he was of the same spirit with those that did indeavour heretofore to put all the Nation in a flame, and to set every one against each other; and said, <hi>No Treason was comparable to that Treason that was covered with a pretence of Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This being done, and the Jury ready to go forth, <hi>John James</hi> desired the Court to favour him with one word to the Jury.</p>
               <p>They told him he had had a great deal of Liberty and time to speak, but now he should speak no more.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>John James</hi> replied, <hi>That if they would not suffer him to speak to his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, they had as good have hanged him at</hi> Bulstake-Alley <hi>Gate, before he came there, and not brought him thither to cover over the matter with the pretence of Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This being spoken, the <hi>Judge</hi> gave him a sore rebuke, and told him he was not to be Judge in the Case.</p>
               <p>Then my Lord and the Judges laid their heads and conferred together, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon my Lord said thus to the <hi>Jury,</hi> or to this effect, You have heard the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; you are to find the matter of fact as it is laid before you, whereof you are the proper Judges, and I pray God direct you.</p>
               <p>Then the Kings Counsel and the Jury departed from the Bar; and at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of the Jury, being about a quarter of an hour, the Attorney and Sollicitor General came back into the Court with them.</p>
               <p>Whereupon the Cryer called them all by name, and the Clarke asked them if they were all agreed; and they answered, Yes.</p>
               <p>Then the Clerk of the Crown commanded the Prisoner to hold up his hand, and asked the Jury, How say you, Is <hi>John James,</hi> who hath been arraigned and tried, guilty of the Treason alledged in the Indictment, or not guilty?</p>
               <p>And the foreman, which was <hi>Charles Pittfield</hi> said, <hi>Guilty according to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then the Atturney General prayed Judgement for the King; To that the Court answered, never the same day he is arraigned, but appoint what day the Prisoner shall be brought, and it shall be granted. Then the Atturney and Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citor conferred together, and the Atturney said, On <hi>Friday</hi> next; till which time he was remanded to the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> Prison in <hi>Southwark.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <head>His Wifes Application to the King, after her Husband was Cast.</head>
                           <p>In the intervail betwixt his Casting and Condemnation, upon the 4th day of the Week in the Evening, his Wife by advice of some Friends, endeavoured to make Addresse to the King, to acquaint him with her Husbands Innocency, and the Condition of those loose persons who had falsly accused him, which she put in writing, lest she might either want an opportunity, or not have courage enough to speak to him, and with some difficulty at last she met with the King, as he came out of the Park, going into the Gallery, where she presented him with the Paper, which on the back-side was endorsed, <hi>The humble Request of Elizabeth James;</hi> acquainting him also by word who she was, to whom he held up his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:204229:13"/>finger and said, <hi>Oh Mr. James, he is a sweet Gentleman!</hi> but following him for some further answer, the door was shut against her, which was all she could ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain at that time. The next morning she came again to the same place, where she had not long been, but the King came out of the Gallery to go into the <hi>Park,</hi> whom she followed down the staires, imploring his Answer to her Request, who then replied, <hi>That he was a Rogue, and should be hanged;</hi> one of the Lords attending him, asked her of whom she spake, whereunto the King answered, of <hi>John James that Rogue; he shall be hanged, yea he shall be hanged.</hi> And so she came away satisfied in her Conscience, that what she had done was but her duty.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="day">
               <head>What passed the third day of his Tryal, <hi>Novemb. 22.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Being this day brought to the Bar, according to former order, the Clarke pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded according to their manner, and told the Court, that <hi>John James</hi> had been arraigned and tried, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and had committed himself to <hi>God and the Countrey</hi> for Tryal, and by the Country was found guilty of the Crimes and Treasons alledged against him in the Indictment; and then it was demanded of <hi>John James</hi> what he had to say for himself, why sentence of death should not be passed upon him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law, to which <hi>John James</hi> answered, That he had not much to say, onely two or three Scriptures he would leave with them. The first Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was the 26 <hi>Jer. v.</hi> 14, 15. <hi>As for me, do as seemeth good unto you; but know you for a certain, that if ye put me to death, you shall surely bring innocent blood up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your selves, and upon this City, and upon the inhabitants thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The second Scripture was the 116. <hi>Psal.</hi> 15. <hi>Precious in the sight of the Lord is the death of his Saints.</hi> He also minded that good word of the Lord, <hi>He that toucheth the Lords People, toucheth the apple of of his eye.</hi> He told them he had not more to say for himself, onely one word for the Lord, and so he had done. <hi>That Jesus Christ the Son of God, was King of</hi> England, Scotland <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and of all the Kingdoms of this World.</hi> Which being spoken, they silenced him, and the Court proceeded to sentence, and the Iudge pronounced sentence according to the Law, and said thus;</p>
               <p>John James, <hi>Thou hast been here Indicted, Arrained, and Tryed as a false Traytor to his Majesty, his Crown and Dignity, and hast put thy self upon the Tryal of God and the Country, and the Country have found thee Guilty; and therfore</hi> John James <hi>thou art to be carried from hence to Prison, and from thence to the place of Execution, and there to be Hanged by the Neck, and being yet alive, to be cut down, and thy Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els to be taken out (a fire being prepared) and to be burnt before thy face, and thy Head to be severed from thy Body, and thy Body to be quartered, and thy Head and Body to be disposed according to the Kings pleasure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This being done <hi>John James</hi> had onely time to say, <hi>Blessed be God, whom man hath condemned, God hath justified.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="accounts_and_fees">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:204229:13"/>
            <head>Some Account of the Fees and Charges demanded and paid by <hi>John James</hi> to the Officers and Jaylors, during his Tryal and Imprisonment.</head>
            <p>THat notwithstanding his great poverty, who (as it was well known) what through the means of his
<note n="*" place="margin">He was for some years a Small-Coal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but not able to undergo that Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, by reason of weaknesse (though the most profitable to him of any other) was constrained to undertake Ribbon-weaving, his former Profession, which scarcely afforded him Bread.</note> Calling, but especially the weakness of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy) had much adoe for this many years to get Bread for his Family, these following Fees were exacted from him. First (besides the Charges and Fees paid by him in <hi>Newgate</hi>) upon his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignment at <hi>Westminster,</hi> and first Commitment to the <hi>Kings-Bench-Prison,</hi> the Tipstaffe-men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of him 13 s. for the Judges Clerks, their own and Officers Fees; and 1 s. for his Prison in the <hi>Kings-Head Tavern</hi> in <hi>Westminster,</hi> which they demanding with rigor, he told them he was a poor man, and had it not to give them; and that they would have his Life, and he thought that might suffice them: but they would abate him nothing; for their Fees (they said) they must have; Whereupon he was constrained to borrow the same at <hi>Westminster</hi> to pay them.</p>
            <p>Upon his coming to the <hi>Kings-Bench-Prison,</hi> Sir <hi>John Lenthal</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of him for Fees the sum of 15 s. and then turned him into a Yard where it rained upon him; and after, (for some shelter he got amongst them in an Alehouse) he paid 3s. 6 d.</p>
            <p>After he was cast for his Life, the Tipstaff-men belonging to the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> at <hi>Westminster</hi> demanded his Cloak of him, which he refusing to give, they took by violence, saying, <hi>It must be divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst several of them;</hi> which afterwards they offered to sell him: but he told them he had but a little time to live, and those Cloaths he had should now serve him. After his return to the <hi>Kings-Bench-Prison,</hi> he was constrained to pay 5 s. to keep in his former Prison-Chamber, and they forced him also to dyet a man they put with him to look after him during his stay there.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:204229:14"/>
            <p>And all the time of his Tryal they would hurry him to Alehouses, and still make him pay for all; and put him to all charges of going by Water, when he was brought to and from his Tryals.</p>
            <p>Further, His Wife was constrained to pay to <hi>Hicks</hi> the Keeper of the <hi>Presse-yard,</hi> the sum of 16 s. for his Chamber-rent during his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance there, which was not above three or four dayes.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Hangman</hi> also the day before his Execution, came to demand Money, that he might be favourable to him at his Death: He asking what would satisfie him? the <hi>Hangman</hi> demanded Twenty pounds; but <hi>John James</hi> pleading poverty, he fell to Ten pounds; but in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion told him, if he would not give him Five pounds, he would tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture him exceedingly: To which <hi>John James</hi> said, he must leave that to his mercy, for he had nothing to give him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speeches">
            <head>Some occasional Speeches in the Kings-Bench Prison upon his first Commitment there.</head>
            <p>A Friend coming to visit him at the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> and finding him in his Bed, went to his Bed side and asked him how he did? He then made relation of the several wayes that God and man had taken with him: told that Friend, that touching his Spirit he had much to do while in <hi>Newgate;</hi> that one whole day and night he was assaulted with very horrible Temptations, and sometimes was much pressed to make known to his Brethren what he met withal; but this Satan hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred for a long time, telling him it would but expose him to be slight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, &amp;c. But at last the Lord overcame, and he did acquaint them with his Condition, who immediatly betook themselves to Prayer for him, and God was near unto them, and broke in upon him with that word, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.5. <hi>Although my house be not so with God, yet he hath made with me an everlasting Covenant, ordered in all things and sure;</hi> which came with wonderfull efficacy, and (said he) for present set me into perfect liberty from all my fears: but in some time Satan came on again, and would endeavour to weaken the force of the Word to him, by shewing him how weak and inconsiderable he was, and short of <hi>David,</hi> to whom that word was spoken: But this Cloud was quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blown over, and the Lord by two words of Scripture fully answered
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:204229:14"/>all; one of which was, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12. If there be first a willing mind it is accepted according to that a man hath, and not according that he hath not; and the other, that word of the Apostle, <hi>It is God who worketh in us both to will and to do, according to his good pleasure.</hi> And proceeding to acquaint his Friend with the Lord's wayes further with him, he said, I was after this brought from <hi>Newgate</hi> to this place, where, upon my first coming, I was dealt hardly with, and first put into a place where it rained upon me; complaining of this. I had leave to go into an Alehouse, which liberty I purchased with my Money; in which place I was attended from three till nine of the clock with cruel mockings, by one company after another; and afterwards, though I desired to be alone, yet could not obtain it, but would have put me with a very unsuitable company; yet with much ado obtained the company, whose civilities I cannot but acknowledge, though I would rather have been alone; and truly for some time I was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and said, as he of old, <hi>Why should I live any longer? Lord, take away my Life,</hi> (1 <hi>King.</hi> 19. 5.) But this also the Lord in some little time rebuked, and I had much calmness in my spirit, and very suddenly by Grace arrived to my Rejoycings in God, and now I bless the Lord I am well; sometimes I am putting the Halter about my neck, and putting the Sled before my eyes, to see if it will terrifie me; but through Grace, they are not at all terrible (as yet) to me; and he hoped the Lord would keep him to the end, or words to this purpose: speaking also to the same Friend, with admiration that such a poor contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible wretch as he was, should be called forth into such service for the Lord. And as to them that sought his Life, there was no advantage could accrue to them thereby, they were not like to get one peny by him, having for these eight years been put to such exigencies to get a livelihood, that many a night he has not been able to take his rest, for the sore and painful labour he had taken the day before with his weak body, to get food for his poor Family; but if the Lord would glorifie Himself by such a worm, he desired to be given up to his dispose.</p>
            <p>After he was carried from the Court, being found guilty, he was asked how it was with him? he answered, Very well, I bless the Lord; I am a great deal more at ease in my mind than I was before, for the Verdict of the Jury hath not at all terrified me.</p>
            <p>Another Friend visiting him in the same place, found him exceeding chearful, and much filled with the sence of the goodness of the Lord,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:204229:15"/>declaring in these very expressions, that he could truly say, Whatever the Lord had spoken of in his blessed Word, in relation to any tryals he had hitherto met withal, He had been every way as good as His Word.</p>
            <p>Some other Friends visiting him at the same Prison, after some dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, he desired them not to be troubled, for the Lord had compast him about that he had neither fear nor torment, yet (he said) he had look'd upon all their Instruments of death, and was filled with Joy and Peace unutterable, but when he had any thoughts of living he had nothing but trouble and distraction; for alas (said he) what will my Life signifie? it will signifie but little; but my Blood will cry aloud, it will speak louder than all my Life. I have spoke many a time at a higher rate for the Kingdom of Christ than I did then, but my hour was not come.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speeches">
            <head>Some Speeches uttered by him in the Dungeon in <hi>Newgate,</hi> after the Sentence was pronounced against him.</head>
            <p>ONe visiting him in that place, expressed much trouble on his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, and could not refrain weeping; who came to the party smiling and said, I beseech you let me not see any of this, for all is well, and therefore forbear I beseech you such carriage, which will too much encourage the enemies of the Lord; therefore I pray you let me not see a sad countenance from any of you.</p>
            <p>To several he uttered these words; O saith he, this poor weak bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy has been often near the gates of death in my own thoughts, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and now that the Lord should make choice of so poor a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cass to put it off at such a rate, Oh (said he, with much rejoycing) blessed be God! let him take it.</p>
            <p>Two of his Fellow-prisoners coming unto him at that place, found him at Prayer with some Friends, who observed that his heart was much enlarged in Thanksgiving and Praises for that choice Help and Assistance the Lord had given him in the Work he had been called to, who after he had ended, saluted them, rejoycing greatly to see them; telling them of his hardships he had endured since he was taken from them, and also spake of the goodness of the Lord, which he judged to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:204229:15"/>be great towards him, in that he was supported with suitable strength, and made willing to do the good pleasure of his Father, either in Life or Death; and also said, he had gotten the start of his Brethren, and was going to a place where the <hi>Wicked cease from troubling,</hi> and <hi>where the Prisoners be at rest,</hi> (Job 3.17, 18.) Declaring further to them, that God had been eminently with him, in delivering him from all the fears he lay under while the Tryal was upon him; and although it was hard to flesh and blood to look the King of Terrour in the face, yet when the Lord brought him to it, it was made easie to him; for which he thanked God, and bid his Friends be encouraged, saying, That his dear Lord had helped him over two of his steps, and now he had but one more before he should be free from all that care and fear of dishonouring God, or grieving his People in the Work he was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to: and while he was speaking of the Goodness of the Lord to him in an admiring manner, that God should choose and own such a Contemptible creature as he was, he presently reflected upon himself, fearing lest he might be too much lifted up, but withal saying, he was now going to a place where his sins should trouble him no more.</p>
            <p>Another Friend visiting of him in that place, asking him how he did? said, I blesse God I am well, never better in all my life. I'le tell thee Brother, never a poor creature hath more dreaded this condition than I have done; I have been afraid of a Prison, my heart would tremble to think of it; I would have gone out of the Land to have escaped a Prison; but now it is all gone, every cloud is blown over; I bless God, I do no more fear this Death, than to lye down upon this Bed. And to another he said, The Sentence that day was no more to him than the eating of those Raisons in his hand, saying, O how good is God! there is ground of encouragement in the Lords dealing with such a poor worm as I, for all the Saints to trust in Him in every con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            <p>Upon the Seventh day in the morning, being the day after his Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, some Friends coming to see him before he was unlock'd, none being in the Room but his Wife and himself, he was in prayer for some good time, and that in more than ordinary enlargement, (though the said Friends could only hear some sound of words;) after he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, and the Door being opened, being asked how he did, and how it was with him in his spirit? his answer was, Very well I bless the Lord, never better in all my life; my Wife and I have had the best
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:204229:16"/>morning that ever we had, we have been giving up one another to the Lord; and I blesse the Lord, he hath made us as willing to part one from another, as ever we were to come together.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speeches">
            <head>Some Passages and Speeches in the Presse-yard in <hi>Newgate,</hi> after his removal from the Dungeon, three or four dayes before he suffered.</head>
            <p>UPon the first day of the week, after the Sentence of Condemnation was passed upon him, several Friends being come to see him, he told them that with the help of the Lord he would now finish that Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course amongst them, that he was upon at <hi>White-Chappel</hi> when he was taken Prisoner; for then (he said) he was pulled down before he had gone far in it, and so he read the Scripture to them.</p>
            <p>The Scripture was,</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>6. last verse.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>For you are bought with a Price, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>In the opening of which blessed portion of Truth, he was made a choice blessing to them that were with him; his words came upon them like the small rain upon the tender herbs, and as the dew upon the grasse.</p>
            <p>He first treated of the great cost the Almighty was at to redeem our bodies and spirits, as to what the Son of his Love underwent upon that account. And, secondly, What it was to glorifie God in our bodies and spirits, as to obedience in respect to the Rule of Gods Word, and that we were in great danger to fall short in our duties therein, and except we had more than ordinary zeal and watchfulness, we might lose our holy frames of spirit, &amp;c. But that which was most considerable in the Conclusion, he treated of glorifying God in the body, by giving it up in the spirit to suffer for Righteousness sake, shewing how many Prophets, Apostles, and precious Saints had glorifie God that way, and had great joy in that service; and that our dear Lord Jesus was perfect through sufferings, and how he did rejoyce in that he had a body given him to do the will of God, not only as to obedience to the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptive</hi> Will of the Father, but also to fulfill all the <hi>Prophecies</hi> that had been spoken of Him, that related to his suffering, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:204229:16"/>
            <p>And then said, He did not think when he began to speak from that Text in <hi>White-Chappel,</hi> that he should so suddenly have been called to glorify God in his body in that way that he was now likely; yet, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuch as it was his Fathers good pleasure so to honour such a poor worm as he was, to give him, not only to <hi>believe</hi> in his Name, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to <hi>suffer</hi> for his Sake, his soul did rejoyce in the Lord; and as he had a Baptism to be baptized withal, he was straitned till it was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished.</p>
            <p>The Messenger that brought the tidings from the Under-Sheriff of his Execution, coming the second day of the week to him, found him in Bed, and said he had brought him sad news; who raising himself in his Bed, said, God forbid, what can that be? who said, that the next fourth day he was ordered to go to his Execution. He replyed, Blessed be God, that is good news. Whereupon a Friend coming in, he said, Ah! now I can invite thee to my Wedding, for I know now my Wedding day: Upon the bringing of which news that Scripture was presented to him with much power, <hi>The Cup which my Father hath given me to drink, shall I not drink it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the second day of the week in the afternoon, several Friends being with him, he judging that the greatest cause of the Sentence and Condemnation passed upon him, was in respect to his Principle of the <hi>Fifth Kingdom,</hi> therefore he desired to leave with them some of his Scripture-grounds for that his perswasion, for which he was now about to suffer, desiring the same might be committed to writing, which was as followeth. He said,</p>
            <p>I do really judge that the Lord Jesus Christ that is now at the right hand of the Father, shall have the Kingdoms of the World. I shall quote some Scriptures for it; The first is in <hi>Psal.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Ask of me, and I will give thee the Heathen for thine Inheritance, and the uttermost parts of the Earth for thy Possession:</hi> and this He must have by Gods decree, as in ver. 7. <hi>I declare the Decree, the Lord hath said unto me, Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee.</hi> That Christ must have the Heathen for his Inheritance, and the uttermost parts of the Earth for his Possession, is proved clear from hence. There is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther word in <hi>Psa.</hi> 72. from the beginning of the <hi>Psalm</hi> to the end of the 15 verse, but more especially the 8, 9, &amp; 10 verses: <hi>He shall have Dominion also from Sea to Sea, and from the River to the ends of the Earth: they that dwell in the Wilderness shall bow before Him, and his
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:204229:17"/>Enemies shall lick the dust: the Kings of</hi> Tarshish, <hi>and of the Isles, shall bring Presents, the Kings of</hi> Sheba <hi>and</hi> Seba <hi>shall offer Gifts.</hi> Another Scripture is in the ninth of <hi>I saiah</hi> (though I might urge many more Scriptures, as <hi>Psal.</hi> 145. about the beginning of that Psalm, &amp;c.) <hi>Isa.</hi> 9.6. <hi>For unto us a Child is born, unto us a Son is given, and the Government shall be upon his Shoulder; and his Name shall be called, Wonderful Counsellor, The Mighty God, The Everlasting Father, The Prince of Peace; Of the increase of his Government and Peace there shall be no end, upon the Throne of</hi> David, <hi>and upon his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to order it, and to establish it with Judgment and with Justice, &amp;c.</hi> These Scriptures are very clear to prove that Jesus Christ must have the Government. Another full word is in <hi>Isa.</hi> 53.12. (and that by purchase) <hi>Therefore will I divide him a portion with the great, and he shall divide the portion with the strong, because he hath poured out his soul unto death, &amp;c.</hi> That Jesus Christ must have the Government is clear, as he is the son of <hi>David,</hi> Luk. 1.31, 32, 33. <hi>And behold, thou shalt conceive in the womb, and bring forth a Son, and shalt call his name JESUS; He shall be great, and shall be called the Son of the Highest: And the Lord God shall give unto Him the Throne of his father</hi> David, <hi>and He shall reign over the house of</hi> Jacob <hi>for ever, and of his Kingdom there shall be no end.</hi> I judge this Scripture to be equivolent to that in <hi>Isa.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Unto us a Child is born, &amp;c.</hi> respecting Christ as he is the son of <hi>David.</hi> But these Scriptures may suffice for the old Testament. The Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> clearly asserts this Truth of the <hi>Fifth Kingdom,</hi> in 1 Tim. 6.15. <hi>Which in his time he will shew, who is the blessed and only Potentate, the King of kings, and Lord of lords.</hi> The Apostle asserts Jesus Christ to be the <hi>only Potentate, King of kings, and Lord of lords;</hi> which is the very Superscription he brings upon the thigh when He comes to make war with the Horns, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.16. <hi>He hath on his Vesture and on his Thigh a Name written, KING of Kings, and LORD of Lords.</hi> That Jesus Christ must have the Government, that he must have the Kingdoms of the World is very clear; but to the further proof thereof, take <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. <hi>The seventh Angel sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and there were great voices in Heaven, saying, The Kingdoms of this world are become the Kingdoms of our Lord, and of his Christ, and He shall reign for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any now say, We grant that Jesus Christ shall have Dominion and Power, and shall reign for ever, but Jesus Christ says, <hi>His King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is not of this World.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:204229:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> It's true, Christ spake truth, Christs Kingdom was not then in this world, or of this world; but what is this to that? there is a time that his Kingdom must be of this world, the Scripture saith it plainly, I never heard any allegorize this Text, but have been forced to take it in the plain sense of the words; the Scripture saith it plainly, if that word in <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.26, 27. be rightly understood: <hi>For as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath Life in himself, so hath he given to the Son to have Life in himself; and hath given Him Authority to execute Judgment also, because he is the Son of Man.</hi> Again, this Truth is plain from that of <hi>Daniel</hi> (which I thought not to have urged) ch. 7.18. compared with the 27 verse. Ver. 18. <hi>But the Saints of the Most High shall take the Kingdom, and possess the Kingdom for ever, even for ever and ever.</hi> And ver. 27. <hi>And the Kingdom and Dominion, and the greatness of the Kingdom under the whole Heaven, shall be given to the People of the Saints of the Most High, whose Kingdom is an everlasting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and all Dominions shall serve and obey Him.</hi> Now observe, here is two things I take notice of, to prove that this Kingdom is an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward visible Kingdom. First, the Kingdom that the Saints take is from the fourth Beast; the Beast had never to do within any Kingdom but what is below in the lower Region; the Kingdom that the Saints take, which is said to be Christs Kingdom, (in the 27 verse) is an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Kingdom, and therefore not a spiritual Kingdom. That is one Reason. Secondly, another Reason is, It is the Kingdom and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and the greatness of the Kingdom under the whole Heaven; and therefore it must be an outward Kingdom, and must be equivolent to that, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. <hi>The Kingdoms of this World are become the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of our Lord, and of his Christ, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next thing that I have to say, will be as to the Nature of this Kingdom in the Administration thereof, which will be very righteous and holy; which you have clearly in <hi>Isa.</hi> 32.1, 2. <hi>Behold, a King shall reign in Righteousness, and Princes shall rule in Judgment,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Isa.</hi> 1.26. hath respect to the same time, <hi>I will restore thy Judges as at the first, and thy Counsellors as at the beginning; afterwards thou shalt be called the City of Righteousness, the Faithful City.</hi> This Kingdom will be a Kingdom wherein the Laws of God will be the only Laws extant, the Laws of God will be the only Laws in being; and those that shall have the executive power of those Laws, will be men qualified accordingly, moulded according to that holy and just
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:204229:18"/>Law: As to the persons that shall have the Executive Power of that Government, you have in <hi>Isa.</hi> 60.17. <hi>I will also make thy Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers Peace, and thine Exactors Righteousness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next thing (I must but touch upon things) How Jesus Christ must come by this Kingdom; and that is, He shall use his People in his hand as his <hi>Battle-ax and Weapon of War</hi> for the bringing in the Kingdoms of this World into subjection to Him. A few Scriptures (and but a few) as to this, <hi>Isa.</hi> 41.14 ver. but more especially the 15, &amp; 16 verses, the Prophet, speaking of <hi>Jacob,</hi> saith, <hi>Behold, I will make thee a new sharp-threshing Instrument, having teeth; thou shalt thresh the Mountains, and beat them small, and shall make the Hills as chaff; thou shalt fan them, and the wind shall carry them away, &amp;c.</hi> The next Scripture is in <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.20, 21. <hi>Thou art my Battle-ax</hi> (speaking to his own People) <hi>and Weapons of War; for with thee will I break in pieces the Nations, and with thee will I destroy Kingdoms, &amp;c.</hi> I might produce many Scriptures more, that God will make use of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in doing of this great work: <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.14. <hi>These shall make War with the Lamb, and the Lamb shall overcome them; for he is Lord of lords, and King of kings: and they that are with him, are Called, and Chosen, and Faithful.</hi> In the great work of Jesus Christ against the Horns, he hath a Remnant <hi>called,</hi> and <hi>faithful,</hi> and <hi>chosen,</hi> standing by him in this Work, which doth mightily correspond with those two former Prophecies. Therefore, seeing that the Lord will make use of his People as his Battle-ax and Weapon of War; and that they are a faithful, and called, and chosen Remnant, I only leave this one word by way of exhortation to the Lord's People that have faith in these Prophecies, to be looking to the qualifications of this chosen Remnant, and that they have in <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.3, 4, 5. <hi>They sung as it were a new Song before the Throne, and before the four Beasts, and the Elders, and no man could learn that Song but the hundred and forty and four thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand which were redeemed from the Earth, &amp;c.</hi> They that serve the Lord in this great Work, they must be a Remnant indeed, redeemed from the Earth. I press the Lords People very earnestly to look to the qualifications of that Remnant that must serve the Lord, and see how it is with them, whether or no they are a people so qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, a People indeed <hi>redeemed from the Earth,</hi> a People indeed ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from among men, a People <hi>in whose mouth is no guile,</hi> a People <hi>that have not defiled themselves with women,</hi> a People <hi>that are Virgins,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:204229:18"/>and have kept a <hi>Virgin-like Spirit:</hi> And I shall say no more, but leave what hath been spoken as some Scripture-evidence of my Judgment aforesaid.</p>
            <p>In this interval between the Sentence and his Execution, seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral persons of quality came to visit him, both Men and Women, Courtiers and others, whose coming were chiefly to this end and purpose, to perswade him to petition the King for his Life, and further to lay forth his Innocency; and especially one of Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency in the City, did labour much with him to that end: To whom he did reply, as usually to others in that case, That he had discharged his Duty and Conscience already in the clearing of himself, and to the King he had done no wrong; and therefore would submit himself to the Lord, and rest satisfied in his Good-pleasure. The said party of note afterwards urged his Wife that she would petition, if her Husband had not that freedom; and withal, as an Argument to provoke her thereto, told her it might be a means to prevent the cry of innocent blood, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise might be brought upon them: To whom she gave a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar account what means she had already used to that purpose, and what success she had (according as has been before recited) which gave him satisfaction in that matter.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="narrative_of_the_accuseds_behavior">
            <head>Some Collections and Observations of a Friend, that was frequently with him during his Imprisonment, till the time of his Execution.</head>
            <p>HE was for the most part born up in a sweet spiritual rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing frame, and his words were gracious, much rejoycing in the Lord, and admiring at his Bounty towards such a poor worm as he was, inasmuch as he was accounted worthy to suffer for so glorious a Cause, even for Testifying to the Kingdom of Christ and the Righteousness thereof, and against the Kingdom of this World and the Wickedness thereof; and also, in that he was a <hi>Companion</hi> of them that had been so used, he being so unlike them; they being men of <hi>Note,</hi> and he a man of <hi>no Name;</hi> they were men <hi>educated</hi> and of <hi>considerable breeding,</hi> and he <hi>hardly knew let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters;</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:204229:19"/>their persons had some <hi>presence</hi> and <hi>aimiableness,</hi> but he a <hi>poor low deformed worm,</hi> yea a <hi>flea;</hi> and sometimes he would speak with a smiling countenance, rejoycing that he was in his Tryals and Death made so like his precious Redeemer; first, in that he was delivered up into the hands of men to be judged through envy, &amp;c. Secondly, and that Envy procured false Witnesses, to lay to his charge things that he knew not; he himself, with many Witnesses, affirming, that what was witnessed against him was false, both as to the <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>form:</hi> And thirdly, that he was tryed in so high a Court, there being several Judges before him, and four of the Kings Counsellors, besides the Atturney and Solicitor General, pleading against him to take away his Life; and a Jury of Knights and Gentlemen all of the same spirit, thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting after his Blood, and in thus much, like to his precious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, according to the word of Prophecy spoken of him in this case, <hi>Psal.</hi> 22.12, 16. Fourthly, in that they robbed him of his Garments; for when they had condemned him, the Kings-Bench Jaylors took away his Cloak from him. And fifthly, in that he was to be hanged on a Tree, and that his Bowels were to be poured forth like water, and his Body not suffered to be put into a Grave, but set upon Poles, as is foretold of them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>To all his Friends that came to visit him he gave good Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to Perseverance and Constancy in the matters of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship and Testimony; and that they should not fear mans fear, nor be afraid, assuring them, that sufferings from man for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness were not so bad as they seemed to be.</p>
            <p>He did not like to see any that came to him to weep or be sad, he would still tell them, that concerning him they had no cause to mourn, but rather to rejoyce; for the Joy of the Lord was his strength, and he was going to his Father, even to God his exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing joy. But he said to his Friends, they would rather see cause to weep for themselves, for the world wherein they were to abide, for a time would be full of Defilements, and that even the gros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of Popery was coming up to try them.</p>
            <p>The day before he suffered, he had many Friends came to see him, so that his Chamber was thronged one could hardly passe in it from one side to the other; he spake to every company, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:204229:19"/>to most of them particularly, with a sweet joyful countenance, encouraging them much in the Lord, testifying to them that the Lord was good, and that there was no bitterness in his Service; and said, that even that part which seemed to be most bitter, was made most sweet, for in it the glory of Christ was most revealed.</p>
            <p>The night before he suffered he sat at Supper with some of his Friends, and said unto them, <hi>I sup with you to night, but you would be glad to sup with me to morrow night.</hi> And would often say, he had many a night been in more care to get bread for his Family the day following, than for what he should suffer the morrow.</p>
            <p>That night he sat up late till near the middle of the night, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with several Friends; his discourse was very sweet and profitable, rejoycing in his portion, telling his Friends that he should be taken out of the Land of his Labours, and should be at Peace and Rest before another night.</p>
            <p>About three of the clock in the morning he had a sharp combat with the King of Terrors for about an hour and halfs time, but spake no word, only had an inward wrestling that put him into a sweat; a Friend that watched with him read a portion of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to him, which was the 11th of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and therein the Lord discovered, to the refreshing of his soul, how that the way that he was to travel that day, had been travelled through by the Lord's Worthies in the dayes of old, and by Faith they endured both <hi>stonings</hi> and <hi>sawings assunder,</hi> and accepted not of delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance upon mans tearms, because they looked for a better Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection; and afterwards that Friend sought the Lord, And then <hi>John James</hi> declared that the Comforter was come to him again, and had refreshed his soul; and then he made himself ready, and in a joyful frame took his Bible and read <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Blessed is the man that endureth Temptation; for when he is tryed, he shall receive the Crown of Life, which God hath prepared for them that love him.</hi> From which Scripture he spake about half an hour, and did chiefly make forth the blessed Estate of those that endured Torment for Righteousness sake, and how the Lord had given that choice Blessing only to his choicest Children in all Ages; and that it was no mercy to be tryed, if we yeelded to the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; for when he is tryed, he shewed the Lord took great pleasure in those Servants that bore their Tryals, and came forth
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:204229:20"/>like Gold: he instanced <hi>Job,</hi> and the holy Prophets and Martyrs, and our dear Lord Jesus who was a <hi>tryed Stone;</hi> declaring, That it was a way wherein men were greatly manifested to be Heirs of the prepared Glory, and that wherein men did as much manifest their love to God as men could be capable to do; yea, it was the way that our Lord took to hold out his Love to Mankind; And then shewed with great joy of heart, that he was going to follow his dear Lord through <hi>Golgotha,</hi> and to manifest his love to his Redeemer by shedding his hearts Blood for him, and passing that way to the prepared Glory, yea, to receive the Crown of Glory prepared for the <hi>Beloved Ones.</hi> And when he had ended his Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, he kneeled down and prayed, and praised the Lord, and was much enlarged, to the comfort and edification of the Friends that were with him. After that, he discoursed with much joy and sweetness, and said, That the Lord had granted him the desire of his heart; for he had desired and sought the Lord that he might be so far from being afraid of any amazement, that he might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the Shame with joy when it came, and even long for the coming of the Sled; and he said, he did bless the Lord it was so with him, for he did much long for it before it came.</p>
            <p>A little before his going forth, seeing some of his Friends come in who had particularly desired to accompany him to the place of Execution, said, <hi>Here comes my Bride-men,</hi> imbracing them with much joy. But, said he, <hi>Must not the Sacrifice be bound?</hi> one answered, <hi>Yea, it must be bound with Cords:</hi> he rejoycing, said, so he had heard.</p>
            <p>Soon after the Keeper came into the Room, and calling him down to deliver him to the Sheriff, he told him he was a welcom messenger, he had waited long for him; and so he came with joy after the Keeper from his Chamber into the Press-yard, where hearing the noise of the multitude without, said to a Friend, <hi>There would be by and by as many Hallelujahs, as shoutings of the people with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out;</hi> and there they bound him about the back with a new Cord, and so had him into the Street like a Sheep to the slaughter; with a sweet smiling countenance he came into the Street, where he was a gazing-stock unto the multitude, and so being placed upon the Sled, drawn by a Team of Horses, attended by the Sheriffes men and a Company of Foot-Soldiers, was drawn along
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:204229:20"/>to <hi>Tyburn;</hi> the way out of the Town being very foul, he was drawn through very much water and dirt, besides the very much slap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the Horses that went besides him, yet for all this he was born up with much joy and chearfulness, not at all dismayed or terrified.</p>
            <p>Being come to the place of Execution, he asked Mr. <hi>Storling</hi> the Sheriff, whether he might not have liberty to speak to the people. He told him he might, if he would not speak seditiously, (or words to that purpose.) Then <hi>John James</hi> addressed himself to speak as followeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="accuseds_speech_and_prayer">
            <head>The last SPEECH and PRAYER of <hi>JOHN JAMES</hi> at <hi>Tyburn,</hi> immediatly before his Execution, <hi>Novemb. 26. 1661.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FIrst of all, that which I have to say before I go out of this world, is, to remove that which hath been thrown upon me by way of aspersion, as if I were a Jesuite.
<note n="*" place="margin">This Vindication was occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by the coming of a Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier, (and, as some said, one of the Bed-chamber) two or three nights before he suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to know if he was not a Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suite, and if he had not been beyond the Seas.</note> Here at this place at this time are some that knew me from my Childhood, and can clear me in this particular; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I shall only say this to it, That I am an English-man, never was out of the Nation in all my life; never had any knowledge of any other Tongue but the English Tongue, therefore altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uncapable of such work and imployment as Jesuites are usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally put upon, they being commonly men of great parts and learning, which I am not. I shall only speak this in respect of my Parentage and Education, I came of a very mean Family; I may truly say, as once <hi>Gideon</hi> did, <hi>My Family is the least in all Manasseh, and I am the least in the Family:</hi> And in truth I may justly say, my Family, the Family that I came of, it was a very mean Family, the meanest among all the Families of the People of the Lord at that day, as I knew of; and for my Parents, they were People fearing God, those that durst not for their lives, I say, they
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:204229:21"/>were those that durst not for their lives stain their Consciences in respect of Idolatry and Superstition that was up at that day.</p>
            <p>I shall not need to speak any more to that, I came not here to boast of my Parentage; I declare I came of a mean Family, only my Parents were people fearing God, and did to their utmost, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour what they could to bring me up in the nurture and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of the Lord; and I hope my Father at his death had not ought to be charged with by way of blame: and my Mother is yet alive and attained to a good old age, and I trust so she is. But I shall not trouble you more about this matter, for I onely speak this, to take off that which was cast upon me, wherein I judged the Name of God would have suffered had I not cleared my self.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The second thing that I shall say, is, what I am in my Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, what I am in respect of my Religion and Judgment, and I shall be brief as to that. I do own the title of a <hi>Baptized Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever,</hi> I do own the <hi>Ordinances</hi> and <hi>Appointments</hi> of Jesus Christ, I do own all the Principles in <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. about the Doctrine of <hi>Faith towards God,</hi> and <hi>Repentance from dead works,</hi> the doctrine of <hi>Baptisms</hi> and <hi>laying on of hands,</hi> the <hi>Resurrection of the Dead,</hi> and <hi>Eternal Judgment.</hi> These are the Principles that I desire to own, and have in some weak measure been found walking in: I do not only own the Principles and Doctrines, declared in the sixt of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> but I do own the Commandments of God, the <hi>Ten Commandments</hi> as they are expressed in the 20th of <hi>Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus.</hi> I do here, as before the Lord, testifie, I durst not, I durst not willingly break the least of those Commandments to save my life; I do declare that the rather, because I would inform per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons that I do own the Lord's holy Sabbath, the <hi>seventh</hi> day of the week to be the <hi>Lord's Sabbath;</hi> you know the Commandment, <hi>Remember that thou keep holy the Seventh day.</hi> I shall forbear to speak any more to that.</p>
            <p>Again, further, in respect of my Principle (as that for which I judge I am here this day to suffer) That I do own the Kingdom of our Lord Jesus Christ, (to wit) the <hi>visible Kingdom of Jesus Christ here on Earth,</hi> and I do desire to declare it humbly and in the fear of the Lord, <hi>That JESUS CHRIST the Son of God is King of all the Nations in the World,</hi> according to that in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:204229:21"/>upon the sounding of the seventh Trumpet there was a great voice in Heaven, <hi>The Kingdoms of this world are become the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of our Lord, and of his Christ; and He shall reign for ever and ever.</hi> There needs no more to be said, though many more Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures might be brought to prove that it is so. It cannot be a spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Kingdom, the Text cannot be allegorical; for the Text saith expresly, <hi>The Kingdoms of This world, &amp;c.</hi> I shall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour not to tire you with many words; I do not come here (the Lord knows) to sow Sedition, I have it not upon my heart, it hath not been my practice, though this be the pretended cause of bringing me hither; but the Lord knows, before whom I stand, and with whom I shall shortly be, that whatever I am accused of, as to matter of <hi>fact,</hi> I am free from it; I desire you may hear it, and take notice of it, the things charged upon me are notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously false, I speak it as my last words, the Lord that knows all hearts, and one day will call all men to an Account, knows I speak true, both in respect of the manner of the thing charged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, and in respect of the matter, notwithstanding that seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Witnesses took the boldness to swear it in Court. I do in the fear of the Lord also tell you, that I bless the Lord I have not the least hard thought of them that swore against me, I have not the least hard thought upon that account, nor the least rising of spirit against either Judge, Jury, or Witnesses, or any other, the Lord knows it, but have sought their Pardon upon my bended knees, and I hope further shall do it, if God permit. I have one word to say to the People of God, and that is this; I would entreat you not to think ever the worse of the wayes of God, because you see such a poor worm as I brought hither to suffer upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, let not the assembling of your selves together be any way a burden to you; know that word, <hi>Forsake not the assembling of your selves together, as the manner of some is, but be instructing one another so much the more as you see the day approaching,</hi> Heb. 10.25. and let not any of the Wayes of God, any of the Ordinances of God, any of the Commandments of God be ever the worse in your eyes, because a poor worm that has professed them, and has in some poor measure tasted in them of the Love of God, is brought hither, do not think the Words and Commandments of God are the worse for that; And I would intreat you that you would stick
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:204229:22"/>close to them whatever dispensation may be at the door, which no man here knows one or other: but I say, whatever the wayes and dispensatious of God may be, though you may expect to suffer more and more, yet know that was the way that our Lord did go, the Captain of our Salvation was made perfect through sufferings; and the Apostles and holy Christians of old counted it great joy, they accounted it great joy to be filling up the measure of Christs sufferings that are behind. And now my dear Friends, for Jesus Christ's sake be exhorted in the fear of God, not only to stick to those Ordinances and Commandments of God wherein you are enlightned, but take that good word of God, in 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.8. it was <hi>David's</hi> advice to <hi>Solomon,</hi> the words are, <hi>Solomon my son, keep and seek for all, &amp;c.</hi> do not content your selves with what you do already know, but endeavour in the fear of the Lord to be seeking after more. I would further charge every one of the People of the Lord, to have a care of defiling themselves with any Idolatry, with any Superstition, by treading in by-paths that may not suit the mind of God, however it may be accepted in the Land.</p>
            <p>I shall not trouble you with much more, only a word to those that have not yet an interest in Jesus Christ, that cannot call God <hi>Father,</hi> I beseech such to consider, It may be that God hath a mind by the words of a dying man to do their souls good, and I would adde a word; I beseech you consider, though you may not go the same way I go, you do not know how soon God may call for you by death, and therefore I speak to them that are young ones in the first place, <hi>That they remember their Creator in the dayes of their youth, before the evil day is come,</hi> and the dayes wherein they themselves shall say, <hi>they have no pleasure in them.</hi> And to those that are antient, that have spent the greatest part of their time here, in sporting in their own lusts, I would only say this to them, There is yet a day of Grace, <hi>To day if you will hear his Voice.</hi> Jesus Christ is held forth in the Gospel freely, He holds forth his Blood freely; for the worst of sinners are not too old, nor too wicked, nor too great, they are not too unclean for Jesus Christ to pitty; and therefore Friends, consider in the fear of the Lord whereabouts you are, and how the case stands with your poor souls. I have said what I have to say, only I would
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:204229:22"/>desire that I might have liberty to wait upon God, to commit my Soul, and the Concernments of each other to the Lord in Prayer. Then he addressed himself to the Lord in Prayer, as followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>His PRAYER.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>GLorious and Holy Majesty, in whose eyes all the Nations of the World are but as the drop of a bucket, or as the small dust of the ballance; and therefore O Lord, this mighty Concourse of People are nothing in thy sight. Thy eyes are open to the wayes of thy People, and thy ears are open to their Cryes, and thou wilt one day shew thy self strong in the behalf of them that fear thee, whose hearts are upright towards thee. Sweet Father! blessed be thy holy and dear Name, that such a poor worm as is before thee can call thee Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that such a poor worm before thee can come and take hold of thee through thy dear Son. O Lord, O Lord, what am I, or what was my Father's house, that thou hast brought me hitherto? And, ah Lord, this has been but a small thing in thine eyes, but thou hast spoken thy Servants welfare for a great while to come, even to all Eternity. Dear Lord, in the audience of all this People, thy poor worm cannot but blesse thee that ever thou didst call him, and ever became acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his Soul, that ever thou wert pleased to engage his Soul to walk before thee in thine own Paths; and, blessed be thy holy Name, thy Paths do not seem in the eyes of thy Servants to be ever the worse because of this thing, but Thine can blesse thee, Thine can rejoyce before thee, Thine can say,</hi> Bless the Lord, O my Soul, all that is within me bless his holy Name. <hi>And blessed be thy holy Name that thou hast been pleased to keep the Soul of thy poor Servant hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; and blessed be the Lord, that though thy poor Servant doth suffer in the account of the greatest part of this People as an Evil-doer, yet it is not so; yea, blessed be thy Name, thy poor Worm can approve his heart to thee now at the very giving up of the Ghost, that he is not guilty, that he is not guilty in respect of the things that have been by ungodly men witnessed against him: Sweet and dear Father, thy poor Worm can now lift up his face with much boldness to thee, and is as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured that he whom man hath</hi> judged, <hi>God hath</hi> justified: <hi>and now for thy dear Name-sake give thy poor Worm leave, in integrity and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:204229:23"/>godly simplicity to beg one request at thy hands for the poor Witnesses; O Lord for the very thing that they have done, O that thou wouldest pardon them, O that thou wouldest pardon them, O that thou wouldest shew them as much grace as thou hast done to thy poor Worm; and that thou wouldest please, that as they have done their utmost to wash their hands in the blood of thy Servant, let their souls be washed thorowly in the Blood of Jesus Christ; for thy tender mercies sake be pleased to deal graciously with every one, if it be thy blessed will, that have had a hand against thy Servant, from the least to the greatest, from the first to the last. And Father, O that thou wouldest be pleased to look upon the poor Executioner, which is to destroy thy Servant and take him out of the world; O Lord, thou knowest the soul of thy Servant has not the least rising against him; that thou wouldest be pleased, if it may stand with thy Glory, and if he be within the line of the Covenant of Grace, that thou wouldest wash his soul in the Blood of Jesus Christ. O how eminently didst thou please in times past to work upon some of those that were the Executioners of thy People in the</hi> Marian dayes, &amp;c. <hi>this work is not too hard for thee, thon canst work upon him, thou canst make him as chosen a Vessel of thy Glory as ever was in the world; O Lord, if it be thy will, that thou wouldest do it, if it be thy will, O that thou wouldest do it. And for thy dear Names sake remember all thy People in this Land; Lord remember all thy People in</hi> Scotland, <hi>and in</hi> Ireland, <hi>and all thy People up and down the Countries; O Lord, thou hast a Remnant that fear thy Name, thou hast a Remnant that fear thy Name in truth, good Lord keep their hearts close to thee, fit them for any tryal, for any hard dispensation that may be coming upon them. Sweet and dear Father, cement thy People, let thy Peoples hearts be one; Lord, remove those Controversies, Lord, close up all those Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, Lord grant there may be no more rending among thy People; O Lord, what differences there may be among thy People in respect of some Circumstances in matters of Religion, I beseech thee for Jesus Christ his sake that thou wouldest be pleased to knit their souls as one, O Lord, knit their souls as one, that there may be more love, and more peace, and more unity, and more universal agreement among thy own People. And sweet Lord, remember our dear King, our righteous Redeemer; O that thou wouldest be pleased, according to thy Word, to give Him the Heathen for his Inheritance, and the utmost parts of the Earth for his Possession; and let his Dominions be from Sea to Sea,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:204229:23"/>and from River to River; and let those that dwell in Sion rejoyce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Him, and let his Enemies be brought under the soals of his feet; and set Him, precious Father, upon thy holy Hill of</hi> Sion, <hi>and hasten thy work in order to his Exaltation; cut it short in Righteousness, for a short work thou hast said thou wilt make upon the Earth. And be thou pleased for thy Name sake to think upon this Concourse of People that are come to this place this day, and be thou pleased to set home to their souls with much power, what hath been spoken and delivered by a poor weak Instrument; let no soul come hither this day in vain, but let it be a day wherein thy own People may get much strength to serve thee in any further work they may be called to; and let it be a day wherein those that have not yet the knowledge of thee, those that are Enemies, those that are Aliens to the Commonwealth of</hi> Israel, <hi>and strangers to the Covenant of Promise, let it be a day wherein their souls may Come acquainted with thee; let it be a day of exercising much Power, and much Favour, and much Grace to the souls of those that shall be lookers on, that shall be spectators upon thy poor Worm this day. And now, sweet Majesty, for thy Name sake think upon thy poor Worm; thou knowest, thou knowest O Lord how it is with him, upon what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count he is brought hither, the Lord knows it is not so: Father, wilt thou be pleased from some eminent Token from thy self to clear up the Innocency of thy Servant, in respect of the things charged upon him; and keep now the Soul of thy Servant upright with thee this little mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that he has to live in this world. And dear Father, O give thy poor Worm strength enough to encounter with the King of Terrors; blessed be God that thou hast been so kind to thy poor Worm all the way from</hi> Newgate <hi>hither; and sweeten to his Soul all that thy poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture has been tasting of, and what thy poor One is entring into; let him know what it is to enjoy those Mansions that our sweet Lord went to prepare; and indeed and in truth let thy poor Worm know what it is to be a Child, what it is to be an Heir, what it is to be a Co-heir with Jesus Christ: O that thou wouldest please to give some sweet tasts of thy holy Spirit to thy poor Worm, whereby his Soul, whilst in this world, whilst in this place, might be well satisfied, and more strongly assured than ever, that he is coming to thee: Blessed be God, blessed be God, thy poor Worm knows he is thine, thy poor Worm knows he is thine. And now dear and tender Father, think upon thy poor Worm, think upon the Tryal that at present is upon him; and as
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:204229:24"/>Tryals and Tribulations abound for Christ, so let all Grace and Conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation abound by Christ: And dear God, in the very passage be then pleased to sweeten to my Soul the very passage; let not the Instruments of cruelty that are provided to destroy thy poor Worm any way scare him, but let there be such an open door into the Glory thou hast provided for thy poor Creature, that thy poor one may know it all the time his Body is in the hands of men; and make the passage very easie, and let thy poor Servant see by Faith an innumerable company of Angels ascend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and descending to convey my Soul into</hi> Abraham's <hi>bosom; Father, let thy Servant see that there are as many Angels ready to attend and receive the Soul of thy Servant, as people here to look upon him. And now sweet Father, for thy dear Name sake hear what has been spoken here, hear what has been spoken by thy poor Worm, and be thou pleased to be far more gracious than what thy poor Creature is able to beg of thee; and all upon the account of thy dear Son, the Saviour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer of thy poor Worm, to whom he is coming to live with to all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; To whom be Glory and Praise, Power, Dominion, and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, this day and for evermore.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>After this he said he could not speak more, being very much tired, and his body brought very low. The Hangman said, <hi>The Lord receive your Soul.</hi> He replyed, <hi>I thank you.</hi> Then another said, This is a happy day. He said, <hi>I blesse the Lord, it is so.</hi> The other said, The Lord make your passage easie; he said, <hi>I trust he will so.</hi> One asked if he had any thing to say to the Sheriff? he said, <hi>No, but only thank him for his Civility.</hi> Then the Hangman having prepared him for his death, drew away the Cart, <hi>John James</hi> said aloud, (lifting up his hands) <hi>Father, into thy hands I commit my Spirit,</hi> and so finished his course.</p>
            <p>The Sheriff and Hangman were so civil to him in his Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as to suffer him to be dead before he was cut down; the Hangman taking out his Heart, and burning his Members and Intrails, returned his Head and Quarters back to <hi>Newgate,</hi> put in a Basket in a Cart, and from thence were disposed by the King, <hi>(viz.)</hi> his Quarters to the Gates of the City, and his Head first upon the Bridge, but afterwards (by appointment) taken down thence, and put upon a Pole in <hi>White-Chappel,</hi> over against the passage to the Meeting-place, where he and his Company were apprehended.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="the_accuseds_fellow_conspirators">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:204229:24"/>
            <head>An Account of the Death of several Persons since the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>John James,</hi> known to be active and diligent in that matter.</head>
            <p n="1">1. ONe Capt. <hi>Hodgskins,</hi> Capt. of <hi>White-Chappel</hi> Hamblets, who was with Major <hi>Manly</hi> and the Justices at the Meeting-place, when the said <hi>John James</hi> and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with him were taken, being the man that commanded the Souldiers, and to whom the Prisoners were committed to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to <hi>Newgate,</hi> is since taken away by death in the prime of his age.</p>
            <p n="2">2. One Mr. <hi>Mould</hi> a Strong-water man, that led one of the Company with <hi>John James</hi> to Prison, being one that was heard to speak maliciously in answer to those many Inquiries concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Prisoners in the way to <hi>Newgate,</hi> saying they were Jews and Devils: He also much rejoyced to hear that the said <hi>John James</hi> his Head should be set up in the Street near his house; But before that time he was taken away by death, and not suffered to see that which he so much rejoyced in the hope of.</p>
            <p n="3">3. One Mr. <hi>Stanfield</hi> at the Nags-head Tavern, who was ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them that led the said Prisoners to the Goal, going forth into the Yard to ease himself, and returning, in the Entry was taken lame and dead in one side of his body, forthwith calling for his Wife to help him, who came with others and helped him to his Bed, in which condition he continued three or four dayes, and so dyed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. One Mr. <hi>Brown</hi> the Marshal of <hi>White-Chappel</hi> Hamblets, being the man that fetched <hi>Bernard Osburn,</hi> one of the Witnesses, from Sea, and kept him at his house, and was very active in his Place, being observed also to rejoyce in that work; had his Wife since taken away by sudden death, she being heard to say with much imbitteredness of spirit against the said prisoners, <hi>That Hanging was too good for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. It is also well known that several Bills have been put up in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Congregations in this City, declaring the Conviction of some that had their hands in this business of <hi>John James,</hi> earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly desiring Prayers for them.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>